hello and welcome everyone it's January
26th
2024 we're here in active inference math
stream 8.1 with Richard
seron and we're going to have an
interesting presentation and discussion
today on introduction to beijan
mechanics free energy principle and the
state-based formalism this is part part
one so Richard thank you for joining
looking forward to this presentation and
discussion so to
you hi everybody so yeah my name is
Richard s I'm French working in
Switzerland I'm a PhD student at epfl in
in
loan and just to bring a bit of uh
context uh I'm not working on basan
mechanics we are uh we do have a physics
background but who are interested in
modeling bacterial Evolution and
ecology and what happened is that
something like uh I mean the free energy
principle was always in a corner of my
head and one year and a half ago I
decided to really read about the free
energy principle uh especially if I
wanted to transition to the field and I
do want to transition to the field after
my PhD and so I started to ask many
questions to the people from the f
community and I'm so grateful thanks for
them and also on the Discord of the of
the active inference Institute and at
some point I said that I Was
preparing um a lab meeting about the
free energy principle and Danielle
proposed to have this uh in discussed on
a live stream because there isn't such
material to specifically learn about uh
beijan mechanics and the actual physics
underlying the free energy
principle and so here I am so once again
I'm not an expert uh on the matter so
always refer to the original papers but
hopefully I going to I going to do a
decent job um so without further Ado
let's let's start uh I'm not going to
tell you uh what we where we are heading
what questions we would like to to
address or whatever I'm ra rather going
to start building the framework right
away and at some point what we're doing
doing will become clear
so as you may know there are two uh
formulations or
formalisms um of the free energy
principle the so-called State based
formulation and the so-called path-based
formulation so today we will focus on
the state based uh formalism it's not
like the old versus the new formulation
in fact thinking in terms of path
or So-Cal generalized coordinates of
motion I've been around forever but in
the literature but it kind of came back
to the front scene of the beian
mechanics literature I think anyway
today we will focus on the state based
for uh
formalism so the very starting point is
to write down L equation a generic L
equation so it's literally like saying
let's consider a random dynamical
system very briefly for the people not
acquainted with uh such an equation x
here is uh the state of your system so
it could be a simple Scala if you are
considering a onedimensional process but
in general uh X would be a vector for
instance if I don't know you want to um
to model the 3D diffusion of a a bronan
particle immersed in a liquid
X would be a 3D Vector where components
are the coordinates of your bran
particle and you can see on the left
hand side that we have DX over DT the
time derivative of the state Vector so
that such an equation really describes
or specifies the Dynamics of the system
so many things can influence indeed the
Dynamics of the system if I stick to my
bronan particle example
maybe it is subject to an external force
uh so whatever is relevant here you put
it in F the so-called deterministic term
or flow we will refer to it as the flow
throughout the
presentation however in some cases there
is stuff you don't want to explicitly
model for instance if I stick with my
bronan particle example uh it is
constantly hit by um the molecules of
the med surrounding it hence its bronan
motion right and it would be so if you
want to take into account this termal
fluctuations it would be mission
impossible to explicitly model every
single molecule of the millions if not
billions of the molecules surrounding it
so a convenient way to still take into
account these fluctuations which are
literally thermal fluctuations in my
example a convenient way to proceed is
just to add a noisy term to the equation
so Omega here is uh a random variable
was value changes with time uh with the
appropriate
statistics okay so two brief remarks
before moving on if you assume that the
state of your system changes slowly
compared to the time relaxation of your
um of your fluctuations you can write
the autocorrelation function of the FL
of the noise like that where gamma is
the diffusion Matrix and Delta is the
Delta direct function so what it means
it's just that in that case your noise
is super rough and it's not correlated
in time
basically also second remark you can uh
I mean you can use the central limit
theorem to argue that that that um that
it makes sense to assume that Omega is
normally distributed so that in the end
um the noise is a Goan white noise but
not that in the next next live stream
where we will discuss the path base
formulation of the FP we will Relax The
White Noise assumption anyway so we have
this uh random dynamical system and we
can do something cool with the flow so
the flow f is a vector it has the same
dimension mention than the state Vector
because each component of the state
Vector has its own L equation if you
will and you can decompose it into a
solenoidal and a gradient uh terms so we
before sorry before telling you what
this decomposition is all about on a
technical note just notice that first Q
here is the so-called solenoidal Matrix
gamma is the diffusion Matrix just as
before and the I here in the with the
NAA ey this I of X here is a negative
log of a density so it's a
self-information or surprise we will
refer to it as as the surprise
throughout the
presentation and the density at play
here in this negative log uh density is
the steady state or Ness for nilib brium
steady state density of the system so we
assume that that there is such Nest
density that exists so that if you uh
from a given initial um in initial State
you let your system evolve it will reach
at some point uh unique well defined um
Nest
density and second remark before telling
you what this decomposition is all about
not that usually in the papers the
Divergent terms here and here are put
together on in a third term uh which is
uh which is sometimes called the
housekeeping or correction term but
actually if q and Gamma are not State
dependent these uh Divergence terms
vanish anyway and we uh end up with this
the two remaining terms which can be
nice nicely factorized like that also a
last thing I want to say is that if you
uh you consider the solenoidal term the
first term it is indeed a solenoidal
term you can indeed write it as the
rotational of some potential I'm saying
that because sometimes people get
confused when uh they see a gradient in
both terms anyway what this uh the
composition is all
about uh is quite in fact simple let's
consider uh this nice 2D single moded uh
Nest
density okay so the flow and more
specifically the gradient uh component
of the flow which is here the vertical
flow will drive the system towards its
mode while fluctuations kind of push it
away but it's not the only flow there is
also the solenoidal flow which is here
the which is here called the horizontal
flow which uh will make the system kind
of converge to its its mode in um with
ever decreasing cycles and so if you
want to get some more intuitions on this
solenoidal flow what we can do is to
remove the
fluctuations so all the entries of gamma
the diffusion Matrix go to zero and this
means that we would not have any
gradient flow anymore we end up with
only the solenoidal flow and if we do
that uh the system will uh just follow n
Contour circulation on the nest density
that's the bottom right um panel here
where the Solen the solenoidal flow
sorry kind of drives the system on this
circulation here so a small remark about
this solenoidal flow because it kinds of
um Drive the system in um in this simple
example in either clockwise or anti
anticlockwise Direction in a
irreversible fashion irreversible in the
statistical physics
sense um so it breaks detail balance and
so on people sometimes view this
solenoidal flow as the writing the
Symmetry breakings ubiquitous in living
systems
anyway okay so before using this
decomposition of the flow to do some
cool stuff I need to introduce some
stuff so I will have to go through a
couple of things of Notions one after
the other and afterwards I will um we
will put everything together and
actually derive the free energy
principle so the first thing I want to
uh introduce is the notion of Spar
coupling so let's say that in my state
Vector X here I have a subset of
variables this mu here we refer to as
the internal States and they specifies
the state of some
subsystem called me so I mean you get
the idea the the idea is that we have
like an organism
an agent the bacteria in my schematic
and these variables here literally
specifies the internal states of my
bacteria and this
bacteria uh is in a given environment
Niche whatever so there is this other um
subsets of variable we refer to as the
external states and which corresponds to
the external uh world the the external
States of the back of the bacteria and
the idea here is that these two
subsystems are uh are not connected to
each other so when I'm saying that two
variables are not connected to each
other I just mean that um their
respective flows do not take the other
one state as argument so they do not
influence each other basically in fact
they are indirectly connected to other
thanks or through a third subsystem we
refer to as the blanquet the mark of
blanquet so that these guys here are
called the blanket States and we will
see in a minute that it it really
corresponds to a mark of blocket in a
statistical sense okay so we have this
um this uh architecture this par cing
architecture here and in fact we can
even go a bit further and I assume that
within the blancet there are two more
systems the so-called sensory States and
the soc called active State a so
basically the idea here is that the
external State ITA they influence the
sensory States s and these sensory
States s influence the internal States
me but not the other way
around and the internal States mu
influence the active States a which
influence the external State ITA but not
the other way around so it's really uh a
sparse coupling architecture inspired by
the so-called action perception Loop
however we you you could ask questions
like why do the sensory States influence
the external States or why do um the
active States influence the internal
States
Etc so we don't have really time to
discuss this I guess you can think of
some qualitative example in biology but
I just want to point out that even
though this architecture is quite
canonical it's not a definitive feature
of the free energy principle and in fact
in the next time when we will discuss
the other formalism we will do a bit of
zy and we will look at other Spar
coupling
architecture okay
so uh on a technical note just notice
that such uh Spar copings are encoded by
zero entries in the Jacobian matrix of
of the flow anyway so thanks to this SP
coupling architecture we have this this
system of four coupled uh lement
equations which respectively describes
or
specify um the Dynamics of the external
state ITA the sensory and active States
s and a and of the internal States mu
okay
so I want to um to say here about the
mark of blanquet thing that under some
conditions I'm not going to discuss here
so for the people acquinted it involves
having no solenoidal couplings between
autonomous and not autonomous States but
anyway I'm not going to go into this
let's say under some
conditions the external State ITA and
the internal States mu are conditionally
independent so they are independent when
conditioned up B which makes sense
because all the informations kind of
Transit through through b however not
that what when I'm talking about
conditional independencies here I'm
talking about conditional dependencies
in the stationary density so basically
if you fix p and you have this
joint uh conditional stationary density
here for XI and
XJ if these two guys are conditionally
independent it just means that you can
write this joint density like that and
so that such conditional uh
independencies are encoded by zero and
in The asan Matrix of
surprisal okay
so now just a bit more of vocabulary
before moving on um note that if we um
put together a and mu so we consider the
couo active State and internal States we
refer to to these guys are as the
autonomous States Alpha and the cool
thing about the autonomous States a and
mu or Alpha is that they are
conditionally independent of the
external States so autonomous and
external states are independent when
conditioned open uh sensory
States and if you add the sensory State
s to the autonomous States so so you
consider the world thing the world
marker of blanquet and the Act and the
internal States we refer to to these
guys as the particular States pi and Pi
constitutes a particle a particle in a
generic sense of course so an organism
an agent whatever a bacteria in my
schematic okay so here I just want to
make a a point to make a bit more clear
what we are doing what this this
approach is all
about so basically here we kind of
Define what it means for something
bacteria any whatever to exist in the
sense that it has its own internal
Dynamics statistically separated from
the the external it does have a mark of
blanket it does have its own physical
Integrity so we have no clue of how it
maintains indeed its its um its
Integrity in the sense that if you're
considering uh real systems like like an
like an actual bacteria or a human being
or whatever it it does survive at a
given in a given time scale
um by for instance displaying I don't
know like active processes contouring
dissipation for instance here we don't
say anything about how it does survive
it just does we do have this pass
coupling
architecture and from there from the
starting point we are going to derive
the the the
necessary uh consequences of such sparse
coupling so basically we kind of ask or
answer to um or try to answer the
questions uh if things exist what must
they do and so if you're a bit confused
don't worry we're going to go back to
this idea later but I just want first to
show you this quote here which tells you
many theories in the biological sciences
are answers to the question what must
things do in order to exist the FP turns
this question on its head and asks if
things exist what must they do but once
again we're going to go back to this
idea later but that's kind of um the
idea of this approach in a
nut so as I told you uh I still have a
couple of things to to present so I will
have to go through each of them one
after the other and finally we will put
everything together and finally derive
the free energy principle so the next
thing I need to introduce is the notion
of synchronization map so very uh very
um generally speaking I'm not
specifically here talking about our
random dynamical system if you have a
linear map uh GM here which gives you mu
from B and G here which gives you EA
from B then uh if G mu here is injective
so that basically you can go back to the
pre-image from the image you can use the
pseo inverse of G mu so that from mu you
go back to B and from B you can go back
to you can go to
Ita so the successive application of the
SoDo inverse of G mu and then of
G is called the synchronization map and
it basically allows you to directly go
to Ita from mu okay so now let's try to
uh to use this idea in the context of
our system so here corresponds to the
blocket states so if I fix the blocket
states I have a
corresponding uh conditional densities
for mu and ITA I have P of mu given B
and P OFA given B and I and what I I and
their um their modes are bold me and
bold
ITA so in virtue of this synchronization
map I can go back to the external mode
from the internal mode thanks to once
again this synchronization map here and
I'm going to give an example in a sec
which is going to to to make to CL
clarify a bit more what we are doing
here but first I just want to say that
in this nice paper by lens Daka uh about
this this this synchronization map
basically everything was Gan but
uh sometimes uh I mean if it is not the
case a laas approximation which which is
literally a Goan approximation might be
necessary to derive a synchronization
map of close form but don't worry we'll
go back to this idea of laas
approximation later just remember that
we have this synchronization map here
which allows you to go to the external
map uh external mode sorry from the
internal mode so for instance if given B
given the blanket
States the uh uh corresponding uh P of
AA given B
follows this nice normal distribution
where bold um bold uh ATA here
corresponds to the mode then in virtue
of the synchronization map I can view
the internal mode mu as parameterizing a
density I write it that way Q mu which
is equal to this nice normal
distribution where the mode is just the
synchronization map applied to the
internal mode to itself and by
construction of the synchronization map
it is equal to the true external
density so you can view the internal
mode as uh parameterizing a distribution
over external States basically thanks to
the synchronization map that's why what
the synchronization map is all about so
just a small point because maybe some of
you are a bit confused here because
we're talking about modes as opposed to
actual States so we we will talk about
that later but indeed uh I mean if I
take the actual internal States at a
given time T they are not necessarily
equal to their modes just because of
fluctuations or whatever so that if I
apply the synchronization map on the
actual internal States it might not give
you the true external mode but anyway we
will discuss this uh a bit more later so
that was the notion of synchronization
map in a nutshell basically so last
thing I want to uh to introduce before
finally putting everything together and
actually derive the fre energy principle
is the notion of variational
inference so very simply let's say that
you have some latent variables or hidden
variable or some um latent generative
process causing some data s so you have
a prior P of AA over the state of these
edden causes of data and you are also
equipped with a generative model which
just designates this joint distribution
here P of ETA and S so you can view it
as a model of how the latent variables C
the
data so the idea here the is the
following you sample some data s and you
want to compute the posterior
distribution P OFA given s so in a way
you want to refine your belief about the
the the hidden code of data thanks to a
new sample data so it's very simple you
in principle because you just have to
apply base theorem right however in
Practical settings the denominate the
denominator here P of s so the marginal
density over sensory data usually
usually requires a monstrous
marginalization so it it's just not
tractable so we can't just apply a base
theorem so we need we need a
method uh which given some variation
sorry which given some some variational
distribution Q also called recognition
density
uh gives us uh I mean we want a method
that makes it as close as possible if
not equal to the true distribution we
want ultimately to compute namely P of
EA given s and this two density so Q our
variational distribution and the true
distribution P of ITA given s are equal
or are more or less equal if their
Divergence can Divergence here is zero
because this quantity here the K
Divergence basically measure the
difference between two
distributions so that's what I wrote
here on the top of the slides finding an
accurate distribution Q in the sense of
finding a q as close as possible if not
equal to the true Target density is
equal to minimize to minimizing this
Divergence
however this Divergence I mean there is
the target density appearing here we
can't do anything directly with it we
can't compute it or whatever we need a
proxy for this target
Divergence and there is a proxy called
variational free energy F in Green in my
in my slide here so f is is equal to
this Divergence here between Q and the
generative
model and the idea here is that you can
decompose this Divergence into the true
the targets sorry into the target
Divergence in red here plus something so
it is indeed a proxy for the Target
Divergence and note that interestingly
enough the second term here is the
surprise over sensory data or negative
log p of s so that f is can be viewed as
an upper bound or lower bound depending
on how you define it uh un
surprise okay so what I just said here
is that minimizing the target Divergence
just means minimizing
F so that's basically what variational
inference uh is all about and not that
usually algorithms require Q to be Goan
or require meanfield approximation or
whatever and if uh Q is required to be
gotian even though the target density is
not gotian we would end up with uh the
best Goan approximation of the target
density basically and in practice it
would mean working with a so-called laas
encoded um free
energy okay so before moving on I just
want to say that uh the this quantity
the variational free energy is in itself
a quite rich and interesting quantity so
you can decompose it in many ways and
each decompos uh provide interesting uh
interpretations for instance if you look
at the second line here you can see that
minimizing free free energy
means um um maximizing this accuracy
term here you basically want to explain
the data I would say but at the same
time you you want Q to Def the least
possible from a prior distribution so
that's that's um an interesting quantity
anyway
now let's finally go back to our sparely
coupled random dynamic system and use
everything we we talked about and
finally Let's uh derive the free energy
principle so here is our system and we
have these four L
equations and the first thing to do is
just to apply the decomposition we
talked about in the beginning so
basically the flows of each of them can
be written like that so I just directly
applied the helmo decomposition we
talked about in the beginning
okay so now um let's try to understand
uh how it works let's talk about the
Dynamics of the system let's say that uh
so there is a momentary
instantiated uh uh sensory State and
let's fix let's say that the sensor
state are fixed and there is a
corresponding autonomous dens uh
autonomous mode toward which the
autonomous states are going to converge
and stay in the vicinity of the of their
mode in the close vicinity if uh
fluctuations are not too large okay but
in fact sensory state with time
changes uh so that the the mode of the
autonomous tape move as well and in fact
it it moves
on its corresponding autonomous manifold
so I'm not going to go into the details
but just have in mind that the
autonomous mode moves on a so-called
autonomous manifold which can be viewed
as a statistical manifold and which can
also be viewed as a so-called Center or
sent manifold so if I kind of rephrase
what I I'm saying here is
that the flow of the of the the
autonomous States can be decomposed into
a off manifold
flow and uh on manifold flow which
corresponds to the path of the mode
itself on the manifold okay so just to
be a bit more clear let's say in my
bottom right uh illustration diagram
here the autonomous states are are here
and I'm I'm uh interested in the the off
manifold
flow so basically I have the this
component here which corresponds to the
gradient flow towards the manifold
towards the mode basically here it's
pretty much like what we discussed in
the beginning and at the same time there
is here this orthogonal uh component
which corresponds to the solenoidal
flow so that's basically the way
the autonomous states are going to reach
their mode here it can be viewed as this
uh ever decreasing cycle towards the the
manifold on which the autonomous mode
move uh okay so that's a bit dense I
guess so I recommend to check the paper
the free energy principle made simpler
but not too simple which kind of um
disuss all this um these ideas about
centor manifolds and stuff so here the
interesting point is that if you assume
a separation of time scale between the
fast flow of the the
manifold as opposed to the slow flow on
the manifold basically the autonomous
State always are are always in the
vicinity of their modes and if you want
to characterize the overall dynamics of
the autonomous States you can focus on
the autonomous mode on the path of the
mode and in the next
slides we will indeed focus on the
autonomous mode um and and by definition
as we already uh discussed the
autonomous mode the autonomous mode is
or corresponds to the autonomous states
which
minimize um surprise here in the last
two lunch my equations because the
autonomous mode corresponds to the least
surprisal autonomous
States before moving on I just want to
say something H we can maybe discuss
afterward because I'm not sure to fully
understand but
basically if I'm here in my bottom right
schematic and so I have this gradient
flow towards the manifold and this
solenoidal flow parall to the manifold
and if I remove fluctuations so all so
the the the corresponding entries in the
diffusion Matrix go to zero as we saw in
the beginning it's it it means that
there is no uh gradient component
anymore and what the system will be
doing is kind of um orbiting or
oscillating around a point which is
which moves the manifold so that's
interesting and I guess that if we do
the exact same reasoning but starting
already on the mode then the wall flow
reduces to the on manifold flow and I
guess that in that case the autonomous
States follow and in fact coincide with
their mode but anyway maybe we we can
discuss about that
afterwards so okay so let's use the
various things we talked about and
especially the notion of synchronization
map we as we said the internal mode
parameterize indeed um a distribution
over the external state so me here um
parameterize a distribution which by
construction coincides with the true
distribution P OFA given B and in fact
thanks to the conditional Independence
between
external States and autonomous States
you can just drop the condition Upon A
and you just have q mu equal p OFA given
F and equivalently you can um you can
write it P of ITA given pi and um the
idea here is that you can view Q mu as a
variational distribution if you want you
can write its Associated variational
free energy so you have this um this
formula here the free energy and because
Q mu is already um already coincide with
the true posterior distribution if you
will the first uh term here goes to
zero and so that F here reduces if you
will
to the surprise of particular States and
surprise over particular States they
appear here in the equations of the
autonomous States so we can do this
identification and we realize that the
autonomous uh mode not only
minimize um not only minimize surprisal
but free energy in general and the way
uh me the internal States will be
updated when the sensory States will
change will always be so that this
Divergence here is zero so that mu is
always always keep stke or synchronize
with or in fact infair the external
States so that you can interpret that
under a generative model which is here P
The Nest density the internal States can
be viewed as performing inference over
uh external States and so
in fact it's not only this Divergence
which is minimized but it's also
surprise and it's not only um only the
internal states which uh minimize free
energy but also the active States so let
me give an
example let's say that the actual uh
instantiated sensory states are likely
sensory States or unsurprising sensory
States and by definition in general the
instantiated sensory States will be
likely sensory States so mu will will
the corresponding mu will be so that
this Divergence will be zero as we just
discussed and at the same times the
corresponding active mode will be so so
you can see composition with the first
uh term here I of a given s and mu a the
in active mode would just be the one the
most consistent with this in inated
sensory States and in fact you can view
it the other way around and say that the
active mode is the mode which yield
unsurprising sensory States so that the
particle can be view viewed as uh
actively sampling unsurprising or likely
sensory States or equivalently you can
say that the particle kind of um
accumulate evidence for its own
generative model and I'm going to say
something about the generative model in
a sec but I just want first to so yeah
this sentence here just sum up what we
said mu is updated so that Q mu is
always the um the best distribution over
external States and we refer to this as
perceptual inference and the idea to in
addition Trying to minimize your price
for Action is called active
inference so a brief note uh we said
earlier that in order to have a
synchronization map of close form it
could be necessary to work under a lapas
approximation so that in that case Q mu
is is is is just the best Goan for
instance of the target density so that
the Divergence here would not be zero
but it still would be minimized so that
the identification here between the two
gradients still hold and nothing change
um nothing changes with respect to our
discussion so here I I just want to say
something about this uh what we are
doing
here basically we assume that we have
our agent or organism that survives
indeed exist or persist in a given
environment let's say at a given time
scale and we end up with the fact that
our particle must be equipped with or
must be must
embody um a generative model which may
or may not exactly coincide with the
true generative process and which
encodes the caal structure of the world
under which it tries to perform
inference and to minimize surprise to
perform from perceptual and active
inference but the interesting thing as
well is that and I think that's
something fundamental that people tend
to misunderstood I guess maybe I'm not
sure is that the generative model also
encodes uh the preferences of the system
and let me explain why if I tell you
that an organism manages to survive to
exist to persist
Etc and so it means that such uh an
organism manages to stay in its ostatic
life
compatible uh States you would be of
course it almost sounds like a topology
uh survive equal uh uh staying in it in
in its homeostatic State that's obvious
right and that's exactly what we are
doing here we assume existence survival
so that the likely state in which the
particle will will persist are preferred
States per se so that for instance if
I'm considering the prior of my
generative model over sensory inputs p
ofs uh sensory outcomes as associated
with high PS so likely or unsurprising
sensory states are three sensory States
states hence when I'm saying that the
active States try to sample unsurprising
sensory States it means trying to sample
preferred sensory States and so uh
basically the particle appears to kind
of uh actively uh accumulate
evidence um uh for its own existence in
a way it kinds of sample life compa to
it kind of stample Life compatible data
if you will and that's exactly the
definition of self- evidencing so I
think we touch here something
fundamental about agency is that agents
are self- evidencing creatures in that
sense okay anyway so um basically I
think that's the most uh interesting
things of the free energy principle we
start from existence and we end up that
such a particle which is coupled to the
world in that way must embody a
generative model which encodes the caal
structure of the world and which encodes
the its preferences in terms of what is
life compatible if you
will okay so just to sum up what we did
here this idea that free energy is
minimized uh you can write it that way
and this is in a way a variational
principle for self organization that's a
free energy
principle so here I just wrote what we
just discussed the agent keeps tracks
and acts on its external mil through
perceptual and active
inference um and note that interestingly
enough you can write such Principle as a
principle of least or stationary action
where the lran which is constantly
minimize the longer path is variational
free
energy
so here I are some concluding REM
remarks I'm not going to through all of
them but the first one is basically what
we just discussed this idea that the
generative model um encodes preferences
if an agent maintains existence its
likely States or its preferred ones per
se the notion of self-
evidencing and I just also want to point
out that this new
approach uh or chapter of physics let's
say consisting in um describing physical
systems as encoding probabilistic
beliefs is called basan
mechanics okay so having said that uh
thank you very much and especially
thanks to all these guys who who helped
me so much especially Lance uh and uh
yeah thank you for um for your uh your
attention coming
back thank you
Richard okay
well while we're settling back in and
anyone is asking questions in live
stream what is your PhD research and if
this is your side project what is your
main project that this kind of relates
to yes so well in fact um I kind of read
about of fre energy principle in my free
time whenever I I had some time and the
what I'm doing uh in my PhD is um so we
have uh a couple of projects the first
project we did was really modeling
bacterial Evolution through so basically
we model bacterial Evolution as a bios
random work on genotype space with um
successive mutations and and and and
successful fixations so that's what what
we are doing it's not related to the FP
at all um and the s
thing we we have been doing is um
modeling uh so basically we had a system
where you have bacteria which can kill
each other thanks to a system which is
called the T6 secretion system they kind
of have needles with which they can go
through the membrane of other bacteria
and and liberate
toxins and they can also bind to each
other so there is like a prey predator
kind of Dynamics and we did like a ltis
gas modeling of such systems so
basically that's what I'm doing in my
PhD uh which is not related to to beijan
mechanics but I would like to to
transition to to the field afterwards so
yeah we'll see how it it
goes a I remember when I thought my PhD
wasn't related to active
inference okay cool
well the work built to an amazing
Crescendo that in its
Simplicity even though you highlighted
it's easy to fly by which is The
Coincidence of the preferences and the
expectations so could you maybe give a
little context how else has that
Nexus of preference and expectation been
approached and is the Fe only and simply
and always that coincidence is that
coincidence upstream or Downstream of
some other commitment that we make like
what are the commitments that we really
make and is that um alignment the
commitment or a resulting
commitment yeah so
um so first of all I think the notion of
um self- evidencing may be a bit refined
with the next formulation but anyway
it's I think that's a crucial Point uh
about the F and usually it's kind of
confusing because when you're reading
the papers and people are starting to
write that the system um sample evidence
for its own existence you're like what I
mean I'm not sure to understand what's
going on here um but in fact yeah it's I
I think the the way I I I um introduced
it this idea that by definition um a
living thing is a thing which which
manage to uh sample life
compatible uh sensory
data is really what uh allows this um Al
align
alignment sorry between the that the
idea that between surprise and
preferences is basically and this idea
that actively sampling um unsurprising
data is in fact and it's not like a
tricky wording it's in in in a way
that's really what's happening it is uh
sampling uh life compatible or preferred
in that sense data hence the notion of
self-
evidencing um but um yeah I think the
world idea here is that we start from
existence we start from the uh from this
pass coupling architecture where the
particle uh managed to maintain its
physical Integrity managed to display a
mark of blanket which uh allows the the
agent to have its n its um its own
internal Dynamic separated from the
external so somehow it managed to cont
dissipation or whatever and so from
there
likely states are states consistent with
the fact that it is existing existing
indeed so I think that's basically the
the the idea but yeah in the beginning
this kind of um line of reasoning can be
a bit confusing but in fact I think
that's very much what the FP is all
about and actually last remark um in a
machine learning Street Talk interview
of Maxwell ramstead he it was titled the
FP as um a physics of survival if I
remember well and I think that's that's
very very much what what it is all about
in a
way awesome how would you relate what
you just described to reward or to
reinforcement type learning
schemes yeah so I I mean I'm not um an
expert at all I could not uh make the
bridge here but I know that um Lance D
Costa made several uh works and
interviews about the the subject and
actually I think there is a very new
paper called active inference as a model
of agency you just shared actually today
um so I yeah I recommend the viewers to
to check them out and as far as I know
but here I'm just I'm just um saying
what I heard is that um any reinforement
learning algorithms can be um can be
framed in terms of active inference so I
think active inference is is a very um
uh fundamental scheme but yeah yeah it's
all good like the reason I ask just with
how you presented it is what kind of
observations do we want to sample that
could be the sensory embodied interface
between the agent and the environment or
you can take more cognitivist approach
and Sample internal observations but
those are just external some other
internal so what do we want to really
sample well if you're even in a position
where you're talking about sampling from
like a utility or a reward distribution
you've already specified a
distribution why not just specify the
existence distribution the actual
attractors and
stationeri of the
measurement and
then
um it's
simpler because there's no proposal of a
secondary intermediate between the
temperature and how good different
temperatures are by going and just
saying it's not rewarding to be at 37
homeostatic temperature it's just
expected and likely and the ball runs
downhill it's actually a lot simpler and
more
General yeah I and I I think
that um it's way more simpler to I mean
the idea here is that the agent has a
kind of world model which as you said uh
specified what what are the the
expectation uh with regards to just
existing in a way and as opposed to uh
designing EXP itly um um um uh objective
functions um uh with the which
incorporates the Notions of utility and
so on so yeah I'm very much
agree um earlier when we were looking at
the
flows and we have the breakdown of a
flow um could you maybe
just
[Music]
um what animal are you thinking about or
What scenario can help us understand
like what's the solid black line what's
the small red line what's the spiral
what's like a physiological setting that
we could associate here to help us
understand that kind of complex
movement yeah
so generally speaking the first thing I
could say is that this notion of
solenoidal flow so it's like in the
schematic schematic in the first slide
where you have you had this EO Contour
circulation on the nest density or here
the the the component of the flow which
creates this sort of spiral here it can
so that um it's these sort of um
oscillations are I think uh the sort of
oscillations or cycles that are aitous
in living systems um I mean I'm not a
biologist but you can uh or not really a
biologist but you can think of the
Circadian cycle or or anything in any
sort of systems there is this thought of
of of um attractor where where you
circulating along and so here
specifically to this to this um a
schematic here I think the idea is that
um um you have so you have you you
basically let's say that uh for a given
sensory State you have a corresponding
autonomous mode and the when the sensory
State change the automous mode mode uh
changes as well and in fact move on its
So-Cal manifold so basically I guess
here you have the mode moving uh on its
manifold and now if we take uh the
perspective of this autonomous States
here we uh converge to the the manifold
to the mode U and because of the
solenoidal uh component of this flow the
way we will um reach it is with this
kind of um ever decreasing
Cycles um so here's the idea and and um
I I really recommend here the free
energy principal simple paper you have
the the flow on the manifold it's just
the path of the mode itself let's say
and you have the
flow of the
manifold was
gradient component is the flow to
towards the manifolding in fact um so
basic so that's basically how autonomous
States kind of um react to to to sensory
data which change the autonomous mode
and I think the well an important idea
here is to assume that the flow of the
manifold is fast as opposed to the flow
on the manifold so that basically the
sensory state are always uh in the
vicinity of their mode and move with
their
mode and um sorry and um and um and yeah
I think that's pretty much the the idea
here okay so let's just say that the
black line is um our homeostatic body
existence life compatible pH oxygen
blood sugar and yeah we are that light
blue dot that's off that
manifold of course if we were far enough
off to be
dead it would be a moot question but
we're off but within a a life um
scaffolding or compatible Zone and now
as time pushes us down into the
right um there are different slices that
we can
trace um we could take the shortest path
the gradient flow directly towards the
manifold so as that plays out through
time it would look like a linear line
converging to the thick block line
or Pure solenoidal Flow would just stay
equally far away from the thick block
line and continue to spiral so that
would look like a cork
screw uh through time and then here when
you have the combined character of the
linearized convergence to towards the
manifold and the cork screw out through
time we get this kind of winding
spiral
so it reflects on me that the gradient
flow is
pragmatic value in that it aligns future
observations with preferences and the
solenoidal flow has an almost epistemic
character in
that it circulates amongst a set of
equally valid
outcomes yet here we're not looking at
the pragmatic plus epistemic
decomposition of the expected free
energy policy selection strategy like
equation 2.6 in the 2022 textbook so is
that just a concordance or where do you
see some of those topics connecting
um I I'm not sure maybe uh but having
said that on this on the the meaning of
the solenoidal part here I know that on
the on the uh I don't remember if it's
in the free energy principle simpler
paper or or someone else but there is an
analogy or I mean they discuss the the
meaning and the role of the solenoidal
flow where they say that it it it kind
of
help um it kind of helps mixing uh the
systems and you can view and they
discuss the metaphor with where you want
to dilute your um your um your coffee
for instance and and you're going to
have this sort of uh Motion in order to
reach the the as fast as possible
the stady state where everything is
diluted but I I um I'm not sure I didn't
think enough myself to provide any sort
of interesting
Insight all good just to have composed
it is very insightful um well you made
choices assembling things like what do
you feel like would have been background
maybe a course or a skill well
background do you feel like you kind of
conditioned upon that somebody might
want to check out and then what do you
feel like you would have wanted to
include in the state-based
formalism um because to to bring it into
a under one hour timing is
very concise so where do you feel like
somebody
could fill in some background to pick up
with you at the beginning and then what
else do you think would make a fuller
presentation I think I mean there are a
few aspects and details I didn't really
uh like fully uh
discuss um well first of all all these
um things which inv here which involves
like C Center Theory a center manifold
Theory and stuff like that
uh we we kind of played U qualitatively
with it we didn't truly go into that and
also if we want to be like full really
full formally speaking
um let's see maybe
um uh well there are a couple of things
where we that we kind of accept without
really checking all the assumptions and
all the deriv derivation and I'm
especially thinking of the of the helm
how DEC composition of f because of
course you need um a steady state n
density to exist to in order to have
such uh a decomposition so here I think
it's it's there is um a lot of stuff to
to check and I mean there is a nice um I
think it's in the appendix B of the
beian mechanics of stationary process
paper by lens where it he he derived the
the helmo
decomposition uh so yeah there are quite
a few things we kind of state without um
derive so it can if people are
interested in in going further I think
that's kind of interesting formal uh
directions um
and
um um
yeah cool I think it'll be a really fun
collaborative project to auma tize and
formalize and modularize using the ACM
onology
and understand a lot of these um
relationships and then the other piece
that that made me think about is like
what work is any of this math doing at
all
just kind of like the the ultimate
existential question here um and when we
condition upon existence we've kind of
like off sourced a lot of cognition we
don't need to make the jump or the walk
or the miracle from Axiom to embodied
existence or to even measured
hypothetical existence so that is left
unaddressed the margin was not big
enough but it wasn't even addressed and
maybe there are even advantages to
leaving
the
um what happens before the
conditioning you don't want to take it
with you after you condition upon it
that's the whole Markov blanket concept
like if you're like well I'm
conditioning on 5 years ago in the
present but also I'm carrying 5 years
with me today well then it's like well
then it wasn't conditioned upon so to
really
condition upon
measurements is an extremely radically
simplifying
maneuver that may change the scope or
the
applicability of the
framework relative to a conception in
which what the free energy principle
does is describe how things come to
be however yeah this rather conditioning
upon it opens up up that discussion and
more
circumscribes this very analytically
tractable setting of the agent and the
environment across a conditional
interface
Yeah by by the way about about the
conditional thing there is now the
notion of you know weak Mark of blanket
that dalon introduced which can of lose
the the the the approach let's say and
and um because indeed there is a
question on I mean does
it apart from the the formal setting we
have here can we really apply to real
systems and stuff like that and um and
also I think it's a physics of survival
uh in
itself uh at a given surv at a given
time scale there is at if I at a given
time scale we survive indeed in the
sense that there is indeed this
partition or conditional Independence
between the internal and external here
is a physics you have to comply with but
we it didn't tell you tells you how the
mark of blanket arise or whatever it's
it's it's it's just not what it is
designed to um to explain um but um I
think generally speaking it's It's
really informative uh because for
instance if you are considering the um I
mean this sort of approach in general I
mean for instance if you consider the
pulum um effect where where you put pum
oscillating on the table and they are
going to synchr synchronize with each
other and I think TAA is Aura did a
paper about that recently um in order to
understand what is going on and why the
pendulum synchronized at some point you
just have to recycle all all this line
of reasoning with the synchronization
Maps that's very what is at play and
what explains why the pendulum
synchronized when they are both on the
same table so I think it it it it really
it is really informative to in order to
understand what is going on when we are
talking about synchronization phenomena
across sparsely coupled systems and also
it gives you I guess the sort of recipe
to understand what it what it um what it
takes to be an agent if you want to
design your uh an intelligence uh
system um and
um but uh yeah the question of how much
useful it is
uh beyond the fact that it's just some
nice formal framework it's it's an
interesting um interesting discussion
yeah and I I I um I uh just two things
first I would like to go back to your
previous question about what sort of
things could be could be discussed
further I think an
interesting uh point we didn't really
uh discuss fully is the notion of
synchronization map
because uh we didn't necessarily discuss
the the the hypothesis and stuff uh
about the synchronization map and I in
fact I think there is um much things
that can be said uh for instance because
we assume
injectivity thanks to the rank nity
theorem uh it kind of constrain the
dimension of the internal manifold here
with respect to the blanket manifold
here and it kinds of constraint in order
to have injectivity thanks to the Rong
nity theorem and so it kind of constrain
the the the in order to say it in a
qualitative fashion it kind of constrain
the the complexity or richness of the
internal
States uh which speaks nicely to uh
other Frameworks like
um uh like asb's laws of requisite V
Varity where you want the regulator
system to to be as um as sophisticated
or as reach to the regulated systems and
here you need the internal states to be
enough uh complex to uh or to constitute
the sufficient statistics let's say to
parameterize to be able to parameterize
the density
indeed um and this um and this U
richness let's say is constrained by the
the cardinality of your
sensory channels if you will U because
basically you need the internal manifold
to be to have the same Dimension than
the blanket manifold or the sensory
manifold to be to have the same
Dimension as the autonomous manif fold
um so I um I mean I think there is many
things to discuss about this um this
aspect here um and and the last thing I
I would like to say about your uh about
your last question about the
applicability of the framework and how
much it's useful has supposed to be a
simple elegant formal
framework I think so you know there is
this um these papers about
um um about like the mark of blanket
trick and stuff like
that uh about how much difficult it is
like to identify what states corresponds
to the mark of blanket or whatever
um and and I I'm personally I'm not
really convinced by this um these
critiques um because to me is like to me
it's like saying to Newton yeah I mean
it's um I'm not sure that I can do
anything with your framework it's it's
complicated if not impossible to model
systems with clearly identified and
separated roads and masses let's say uh
okay fine but we are talking about
Newton mechanics here so I mean I think
it's the the same here it's if you have
a sply couple ROM name because systems
that's the sort of behavior it will
display it tells you fundamental things
about the nature of living systems and
the idea that when it comes to a
specific system it can be quite tricky
to to model it that's another questions
um um and indeed when it comes to the
art of modeling complex systems it's
it's it's interesting and and we can
discuss about how much complicated it
can be to apply the framework
um
yeah awesome I love that it's like the
art of the science and the Art of the
modeling and and the and the craft
especially in the kind of
early handbuilt largely custom stage
like one thing I even wondered looking
through these slides um what fraction of
these representations and
formalisms exist only analytically
and do or is there a code representation
of this exact
scenario or you know are some of these
areas equations that don't
[Music]
have code realizations they're just pure
existing
equations so I mean I think um more or
less everything here can be um can be
simulated even this synchronization
thing here you can um perform
simulations where you can really
literally see within the simulation the
synchronization um and I mean the the
the world thing here can be you you can
simulate such parly cical systems and
and kind of um interpret the dyamic in
did as the way we we frame we frame it
um but
um but yes that's also an interesting uh
aspect it could be cool like in the
GitHub repo in the journal for this
transcript or something like that to to
curate together the simulations that
demonstrate or a minimal specification
for it
um yeah because it's it's is
um yeah and actually there is um I mean
I think it's in the in in lens paper
about um synchronization map the visian
mechanics of stationary process um
processes
paper there there are some simulations
where he shows that um I mean it shows
the the synchronization map at Play and
it shows that basically you can't go
back
to uh I mean if the the the map between
the blanket states to the internet
States is not
injective uh and you apply the
synchronization map to uh the actual
sensory uh to the actual internet States
it gives you like some nevant things and
there are some nice plots from
simulations so that's yeah definitely a
paper to to check out
Co so where do we
land and then how do we sleep exercise
relax to prepare for part
two yeah so I think here's the world
point was I mean the the this world
formulation is in a way about the
momentary the short the shortterm and
the
momentary response to state to
sensor um stimuli let's say um if there
is this uh this um I mean the kind of
instantiated active states are so that
outcomes whatever but in the next uh
video where we will look at the path
based formulation of the framework the
world idea would be to ask what about
path and what about
Future Path and what about the long-term
Behavior Uh and what about planning what
about higher order cognitive
abilities um and we we we will kind of
extend U the scope of what we are doing
in in in that sense um but um yeah I
mean I think from a formal point of view
uh here I kind of introduced many things
varation um varal inference
synchronization map Etc one after the
other before actually driving the Fergy
principle next time I think we will it
will be more straightforward but the the
main Concepts to
to which will be at the core of the of
the framework and which can be confusing
if it's the first time you you look at
it is the notion of uh
of um generalized coordinates of motion
when you relax the White Noise
assumption and that's something that can
be confusing especially for the
physicist because when you're starting
saying yeah the generalized LR gen it
plays a role of an action or whatever
they are like no but LR gen is not an
action what are you talking about Etc
but when you get acquainted with the the
world construction is very elegant but
that definitely something uh people can
started look at before prior to the the
live stream
yeah awesome yeah well it was excellent
you you brought a lot together and a lot
of trails leading off this Trail and the
citations and previous um papers that
that also brought things together
Lance's work and others and it's going
to be awesome to see part two
so thank you Richard thank you very much
Daniel thank you all right see you
bye
by